Guide to the Dan Dodson Papers MC.170
New York University Archives
Dan Dodson Papers
1949-1976
New York University Archives
Dodson, Dan W. (Dan William), 1907-1995
MC.170
1 linear foot in 1 record carton
The Dan Dodson Papers contains various speeches, articles, and unpublished manuscripts written over the course of Dan Dodson's career as a professor and public activist.
Arrangement
The folders in this collection are arranged chronologically, with all undated materials arranged alphabetically. The files are grouped into one series.
Scope and Content
The Dan Dodson Papers document the career of Dan W. Dodson, who served New York University as a faculty member in the School of Education from 1936-1972, when he retired as Professor Emeritus. He was also the Director of the School of Education's Center for Human Relations and Community Studies until 1969. In addition to his contributions to New York University, Dr. Dodson was also a national pioneer in the desegregation process in American public schools in the 1960s, serving on local boards, as well as state and federal committees as a consultant on race relations and education. He was also the editor of the Journal of Educational Sociology, and had more than 140 publications on the subject.
The papers in the collection include various speeches and articles written by Dodson, as well as a number of unpublished manuscripts, all relating to the subjects of education, race relations, desegregation of public schools and American society at large, and sociological studies of New York City neighborhoods. The collection covers the period roughly from 1950-1975, during the height of his career as a professor and public activist.
Biography of Dan Dodson
Dan W. Dodson was born the son of a sharecropper in Panther's Chapel, Texas, on April 8, 1907. Dodson received his bachelor's degree from McMurray College in Abilene, Texas, and a graduate degree from Southern Methodist University in Dallas. In 1936 Dodson became a sociology professor within the Educational Sociology Program at New York University and, but for a short period of time in 1944 during which he took a leave, Dodson remained affiliated with NYU until his retirement and return to Texas in 1972. During this period, Dodson served as the director of New York University's Center for Human Relations Studies.
In 1944 Dodson took a four-year leave from New York University to serve as the executive director of Mayor Fiorello La Guardia's Committee on Unity, which had been formed to deal with existing intergroup conflicts. While serving on the Committee on Unity, Dodson produced a report, which has been credited with abolishing the practice of using quota systems to admit Jewish, Catholic, and black students to universities in New York.
In addition to his work with the Committee on Unity, his position as an authority on desegregation led Dodson to assist in the drawing up of plans to systematically integrate schools in Washington and elsewhere. He was also a major influence in breaking the color barrier in baseball, working closely with Branch Rickey, president of the Brooklyn Dodgers, to hire Jackie Robinson in 1946. Dodson then encouraged both the Yankees and the Giants to follow the example set by the Brooklyn Dodgers and begin to hire black players.
Following his retirement from teaching and activism, Dodson returned to Texas in 1972, living in Austin until his death at the age of 88 on August 5, 1995.
Conditions Governing Access
Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The University Archives received this collection from Dr. Arnold Grossman, a professor in New York University's School of Education, in 2002. Grossman donated an accretion to the collection in March 2019; the accession number associated with this gift is 2019.035.
African Americans -- Civil rights.; Civil rights.; Civil rights -- United States -- Newspapers.; Civil rights movements -- United States.; Desegregation in education; Educational sociology.; Race relations.; Segregation in education.; Students -- Civil rights
- Series I, 1949-1976; 216078
  - Various Published Articles and Pamphlets by Dodson, 1949-1974; 216079 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "The Challenge of Citizenship", March 1949; 216081 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 1)
    - "Human Relations in a Troubled Era", May 1956; 216082 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 2)
    - "Social Aspects of Child Development", March 1962; 216083 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 3)
    - "Are We Segregating Our Children", September 1963; 216084 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 4)
    - "Helping the Child to Live in Today's World and Prepare for Tomorrow" [2 copies], December 1965; 216085 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 5)
    - "Social Change as a New Frontier in Education", 1966; 216086 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 6)
    - "The Church, Power, and Saul Alinsky" [draft copy & finished copy], 1967; 216087 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 7)
    - "Psychological Responsibility in Community Action", 1970; 216088 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 8)
    - "What is Quality Education?", January 1947; 216089 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 9)
    - "Rearing Children to Meet the Challenge of Change", undated; 216090 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 10)
  - Various Issues of the Journal of Education Sociology, 1950-1959; 216080 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Human Relations Monograp h, Center for Community and Field Services, 1952-1960; 216091; 5 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Social Research and the American Community", September 1956; 216093 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Racial Imbalance in Public Education", December 1957; 216094 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Segregation in education.
  - "Can Intergroup Quotas Be Benign", May 1960; 216095 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dodson Speeches--1961, 216097 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dodson Speeches--1963, 216098 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dodson Speeches--1964, 216099 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Religious Education and the Interracial Encounter", December 1964; 216100 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Segregation in education -- Religious aspects.
  - Dodson Speeches--1965, 216101 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Various Newspaper Articles, 1965-1975; 216102 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dodson Speeches--1966, 216103 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dodson Speeches--1967, 216104 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Power Conflict and Community Organizations, 1967; 216105 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "New Forces Operating in Educational Decision Making", March 1967; 216106 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Schools and the Racial Crisis", September 1967; 216107 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Publications concerning racial encounters in public schools, 1967-1969; 216108 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - In Essence: Epigrams and Quotable Quotes in Race Relations, 1968; 216109 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Dodson Speeches--1969, 216110 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Published Articles by Dodson, 1969-1972; 216111 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "A Sociological View", 1969; 216112 (Box 1, Folder 21, Item 1)
    - "Where Do We Go From Here?", June 1970; 216113 (Box 1, Folder 21, Item 2)
    - "Human Values and Education", 1970; 216114 (Box 1, Folder 21, Item 3)
    - "Metropolitan Racial and Ethnic Relations", 1972; 216115 (Box 1, Folder 21, Item 4)
  - Dodson Speeches--1971, 216116 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Desegregation of New York City Public Schools: A Feasibility Study", September 1971; 216117 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Desegregation in education
  - Dodson Speeches--1972, 216118 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Action for the Seventies: What is Our Agenda?", May 1972; 216119 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Dodson Speeches--1973, 216120 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Dodson Speeches--1974, 216121 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "The Welfare Mess", Fall 1974; 216122 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Dodson Speeches--1975, 216123 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - New Challenges to Social Agency Leadership, 1976; 216124 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - "De Facto Segregation and the Neighborhood School", undated; 216125 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "Developing Human Capabilities", undated; 216126 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "Does Community Organization Process Preserve and Enhance the Dignity and Worth of the Individual?", undated; 216127 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - "Does School Integration Conflict With Quality Education?", undated; 216128 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - "Education and the Powerless" [pages missing], undated; 216129 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - "Family Life Challenges in the Modern World", undated; 216130 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - "Ghetto Mentalities in a Space Age?", undated; 216131 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - "Human Relations and Higher Education", undated; 216132 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - "Human Rights and Education", undated; 216133 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - "Human Values in the Inner City: Implications for Jewish Communal Services" [pages missing], undated; 216134 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - "Innovation in Sociological Perspective", undated; 216135 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - "Intergroup Relations, The Curriculum and Community Education" [marked-up draft], undated; 216136 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - "Minority Groups and Public Education", undated; 216137 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - "Preparing for Desegregation", undated; 216138 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - "Racial Factors in Public Elementary Education", undated; 216139 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - "School Boards and Democratic Education" [marked-up draft], undated; 216140 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - "Slums and Suburbs: A Comment on Conant", undated; 216141 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - "Solutions Versus Directions in Race Relations", undated; 216142 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - "The Creative Role of Controversy", undated; 216143 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - "The 'Launching Pad'", undated; 216144 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - "The Power Order and Informal Learning", undated; 216145 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - "The Rationale for the Educational Park", undated; 216146 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - "The School Administrator and Intergroup Education", undated; 216147 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - "The School Drop-Out: A Sociological Perspective", undated; 216148 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - "The Schools and the Civil Rights Revolution", undated; 216149 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - "The Suburban Challenge To Family Life", undated; 216150 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - "The Twenty-Year Legacy", undated; 216151 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - "Urban Power Structures and Urban Education", undated; 216152 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Human Relations Workshop Directories, 1949-1951; 216153 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - In Essence: Epigrams and Quotable Quotes in Race Relations, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - New Challenges in Social Agency Leadership, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Program for Dan W. Dodson: An Evening in Tribute, 1969-05-23 (Box 1, Folder 62)